Guide to the Records of The New York Institute for the Humanities RG.37.4
New York University Archives
- Series III: Audio Recordings, 67170
  - Subseries A: Cassette Tapes, 1974-2005; 67171
    - Democratic Possibilities for a post-war Iraq. A Discussion with Entifadh Qanbar, 28-Feb-03; cuid4179; 180599; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 75 minutes (Box 72, Folder 80, Box Access 10, Item 38)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:38.
      Kanan Makiya, was originally scheduled to talk on this date, but was in Iraq. Entifadh Qanbar speaks in his stead. Qanbar is an Iraqi Air Force veteran of the Iraq/Iran War, former prisoner of the Saddam Hussein regime and the Washington Director of the Iraqi National Congress. He came to the US under political asylum in 1990. This discussion, just three weeks prior to the US invasion of Iraq is directed toward answering questions about democratic possibilities that might result from a, then still speculative, Iraqi invasion.
      Iraq War, 2003-2011; Iran-Iraq War, 1980-1988; Makiya, Kanan; Hussein, Saddam, 1937-2006; Iraqi National Congress; Qanbar, Entifadh
    - A Conversation with Richard Sennett about his new Memoir "Respect", 2003; cuid4180; 180600; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 80 minutes (Box 72, Folder 80, Box Access 10, Item 39)
      Founding director of the New York Institute for the Humanities, Richard Sennett returns to discuss his latest book, Respect - a memoir that chronicles his life from the very beginning in the Cabrini Green projects of Chicago. He discusses some of the writing project and then is engaged in conversation by Jerry Bruner and Todd Gitlin.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:39
      Gitlin, Todd; Bruner, Jerome S. (Jerome Seymour); Sennett, Richard, 1943-
    - Literary and Spontaneous Autobiography. A Discussion with Jerry Bruner, circa 1979-83; cuid4181; 180601; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 47 minutes (Box 72, Folder 82, Box Access 10, Item 40)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:40
      Jerome Bruner discusses the topic of autobiographical writings and what he refers to as "literary autobiography" and "spontaneous autobiography." He reads from a preliminary opening chapter of what would eventually become his 1983 book, "In Search of Mind: Essays in Autobiography."
      Autobiography; Bruner, Jerome S. (Jerome Seymour)
    - Discussion of Poetry with Derek Walcott, Joseph Brodsky and Seamus Heaney, Undated; cuid4182; 180602; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 83)
      Poets Derek Walcott, Joseph Brodsky, and Seamus Heaney discuss their own and each others work between themselves and with the audience in this casual lunch panel. The last 1:20 of side two is different content (discussion of religious understanding in children) that had been taped over.
      Likely related to another recording in this collection Entitled "Brodsky, Heaney, Walcott - Fellows Lunch" (ref779)
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 11:01 & ACCESS 11:02.
      Poetry.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996; Walcott, Derek; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-2013
    - Readings and Discussion with Poet Joseph Brodsky, circa 1980-85; cuid4183; 180603; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 45 minutes (Box 72, Folder 84, Box Access 10, Item 41)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:41
      Joseph Brodsky reads and discusses some of his poems in both Russian and English. A number of the poems he reads is part of what he refers to as a "road show" - an attempt to encapsulate the most important events of the 20th century in poems. He wrote one poem for each year. Here he shares the poems for 1900 to 1914.
      Content changes near the end of tape.
      American poetry -- 20th century.; Poetry.; Russian American Poetry; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996
    - South African Culture. A Discussion with Nadine Gordimer, December 3, 1981; cuid4184; 180604; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 85, Box Access 10, Item 46-47)
      Nadine Gordimer discusses the legal, social, political, industrial, cultural, and literary situations in South Africa during Apartheid. She is engaged in conversation by members of the audience, including Tom Bender, Susan Sontag, Aryeh Neier, Denis Donoghue, and Linda Nochlin.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 10:46 & ACCESS 10:47
      Apartheid; Race discrimination.; Discrimination; South Africa; Sontag, Susan, 1933-2004; Nochlin, Linda; Donoghue, Denis; Gordimer, Nadine; Neier, Aryeh, 1937-; Bender, Thomas
    - The Sounding of the Whale. Discussion and Readings from the upcoming book with Author D. Graham Burnett., 01-Jan-03; cuid4185; 180605; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 70 minutes (Box 72, Folder 86, Box Access 10, Item 42)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:42
      D. Graham Burnett discusses the topic of his forthcoming book, The Sounding of the Whale: Science and Cetaceans in the 20th Century. Burnett explores the depiction of whales in literature throughout the written record and the evolution of our understanding of and relationship with whales and dolphins.
      Whales in literature; Dolphins in literature; Cetaceans; Whales; dolphins (cetaceans); Burnett, D. Graham
    - What Makes It New? A Gallatin Series Lecture by Lukas Foss, Undated; cuid4186; 180606; Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 87, Box Access 10, Item 48-49)
      A Gallatin Lecture entitled "What Makes It New?" Lukas Foss discusses avant garde art movements and the difference between repetition/imitation and novelty/innovation.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 10:48 & 10:49.
    - Hungarian Literature. A Discussion with Author George Konrad, Probably 1983; cuid4187; 180607; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 47 minutes (Box 72, Folder 88)
      Hungarian scholar and novelist, George Konrad discusses Hungarian Literature before and during the Cold War.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:08
      Slavic literature; Hungarian literature -- 20th century -- History and criticism; Hungarian literature -- 20th century; Cold War.; Hungarian literature; Konrád, György, 1933-
    - Mitterand's France. A Lecture by Nicolas Wahl, Oct. 22, (probably) 1983; cuid4188; 247760; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 50 minutes (Box 72, Folder 133)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:09.
      Director of NYU's French Institute Nicolas Wahl discusses the government of France under Francois Mitterand. He also reviews the recent history of France's government and various socialist tendencies.
      Socialism.; France.; France -- Politics and government -- 1958-; France. President (1981-1995: Mitterrand); Wahl, Nicholas; Mitterand, François, 1916-
    - Discussion of "Les Freres Goncourt," with Richard Howard, Around 1984-87; cuid4189; 180609; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 89)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:03
      Richard Howard discusses the literary works of the "enigmatic" Goncourt brothers, Jules and Edmond, and their strange relationships with notable contemporaries such as de Maupassant and Flaubert, Balzac, Gautier, and Renan.
      Prix Goncourt; Literature (French); Ernest, Renan, 1823-1892; Goncourt, Jules de, 1830-1870; Goncourt, Edmond de, 1822-1896; Gautier, Théophile, 1811-1872; Howard, Richard
    - History of Fashion: A Sex, Gender and Consumer Culture Lecture by Anne Hollander, Around 1982-83; cuid4190; 180610; 2 sound cassettes Approx. 140 minutes (Box 72, Folder 90, Box Access 10, Item 43-45)
      Anne Hollander discusses the history of fashion, gender and consumer culture. Going back to Europe in 1300, Hollander narrates a slide show, illustrating how fashion evolved over time. The last half hour (approximately) is dedicated to question and answer.
      Access copy available on 3 CDs: ACCESS 10:43 - ACCESS 10:45.
      Fashion; Fashion -- History; Fashion in art; Genders and sexualities in the social sciences; Gender, sexuality & culture; Culture.; Sexuality; Hollander, Anne
    - Inventing Times Square Lecture Series (I). "The Urban Face of Capitalism." A Lecture by David Harvey, Oct. 27, 1988; cuid4191; 180612; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 92, Box Access 10, Item 58)
      David Harvey gives the innagural lecture in the Inventing Times Square Conference/Lecture series. The theme of this first session in the series is "Developing a Place: The Dynamics of Commercial Culture." His lecture, "The Urban Face of Captialism" discusses political and economic processes in general and more specifically their relationship to urban and commercial development. This leads to themes of the organization of space and time in societies in general and capitalist societies in particular.
      During the 1988-89 academic year, the NYIH held the monthly conference series, Inventing New York. This consisted of day-long sessions with lectures, panels of scholars and commissioned papers discussing different themes in the "emergence of modern American commercial culture" using Times Square as a representative focal point.
      The proposal describes the the various themes, stating, "Panels one and two deal with the economic context in which entrepreneurial development was made possible, and with the roles of particular promoters and entrepreneurs. The next two panels examine the spatial and aesthetic forms of this new world of cultural consuption (i.e. the architecture, interior design and aesthetic character of the major institutional stores), and the performance dimension of theatre, deance and show that created the excitement and drew the crowds. The concluding sessions challenge to existing moral conventions, and the efforts of these new forces in the culture to give their energies protective coloration -- first by flying the flag and then by appealing to new kinds of cosmopolitan sophistication."
      This proposal became manifest in the following themed conferences:
      I. Developing a Place: The Dynamics of Commercial Culture II. Producing a Place: Promoters, Politicians, Entrepreneurs III. Imaging a Place: The Aesthetics of the Commercial World IV. The Life of a Place: Performance and Pleasure V. Policing a Place: The Politics of Respectability VI. Remembering a Place: From Patriotism to Cosmopolitanism
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:58
      Popular culture -- American influences; Commercialism; Urbanization.; Community development, Urban; urban development; Sociology, Urban.; Times Square (New York, N.Y.); Harvey, David, 1935-
    - Inventing Times Square Lecture Series (III). "Urban Tourism and the Commercial City." A Lecture by Neil Harris., Dec. 15, 1988; cuid4192; 180620; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 115 minutes (Box 72, Folder 97, Box Access 10, Item 53-54)
      The third in a series of six monthly lecture/conferences on Inventing Times Square, Neil Harris gives a lecture entitled "Urban Tourism and the Commercial City." The them of this session is Imaging A Place: The Aesthetics of the Commercial World. Harris discusses the development of tourism in New York City and the modern-day tourism industry more generally.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 10:53 & ACCESS 10:54
      urban development; Sociology, Urban.; Community development, Urban; Times Square (New York, N.Y.); Tourism.; Popular culture -- American influences; Commercialism; Urbanization.; Harris, Neil
    - A Tribute to W.H. Auden, October 18, 1983; cuid4193; 180621; New York Institute for the Humanities; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 98, Box Access 10, Item 55-56)
      Recording of A Poet's Tribute to W.H. Auden. Co-sponsored by the New York Institute for the Humanities and the Academy of American Poets, the event is introduced by the directors of those institutions (Mrs. Hugh Bullock and Mr. Richard Sennett. Prominent poets read their favorite Auden poems on the 10th anniversary of his death. With the exception of Christopher Isherwood who read first, the participants read in alphabetical order as follows: John Ashbery, Joseph Brodsky, Amy Clampitt, Alfred Corn, Marilyn Hacker, Anthony Hecht, John Hollander, Richard Howard, James Merrill, Howard Moss, May Swenson, Mona Van Duyn, and Derek Walcott.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 10:55 & ACCESS 10:56
      Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973. Poems; Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973. Poems. Selections; American poetry -- 20th century -- History and criticism.; American poetry -- 20th century.; English poetry.; Poetry.; Auden, W.H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996; Clampitt, Amy; Ashbery, John, 1927-; Corn, Alfred, 1943-; Hacker, Marilyn, 1942-; Hecht, Anthony, 1923-2004; Hollander, John; Howard, Richard; Moss, Howard, 1922-1987; Merrill, James, 1926-1995; Van Duyn, Mona; Swenson, May; Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; Walcott, Derek; Academy of American Poets; Sennett, Richard, 1943-; Bullock, Marie, 1911-1986
    - Transitions for de Tocqueville's Tapes, Undated; cuid4194; 180622; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 8 minutes (Box 72, Folder 99, Box Access 10, Item 57)
      During the de Tocqueville conference, which was recorded on 1/4" open tape reels, this tape was used to record the portions of the event that took place while the reel was being changed. These are the ends of sides 1 and 2 of tape 1. Recorded back to back, each section is approximately 4 minutes.
      The other reels from this event are available as part of this collection (Box 75, folders 45 & 46).
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:57
      Bender, Thomas; Neier, Aryeh, 1937-; Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1805-1859
    - Depression Too Is a Thing with Feathers, Sept. 21, 2001; cuid4195; 180625; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 70 minutes (Box 72, Folder 101)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:36
      Author Andrew Solomon discusses the topic of depression, a subject on which he first wrote an influential piece that was published in the New Yorker. He subsequently wrote an acclaimed book on the subject entitled The Noonday Demon.
      Depression, Mental; Solomon, Andrew, 1963-
    - In the Name of Picasso., Around 1998; cuid4196; 180630; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 68 minutes (Box 72, Folder 102)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:37
      Rosalind Krauss discusses the life and works of Pablo Picasso. She had recently written a book entitled The Picasso Papers. While the tape itself is labeled "William Finnegan", he only introduces Krauss.
      Art.; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973; Krauss, Rosalind E.
    - Mid 19th Century Urban American Commercial Culture, Probably 1986; cuid4197; 180631; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 95 minutes (Box 72, Folder 103)
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 11:39 & 11:40
      Author and Columbia University Professor of History Betsy Blackmar leads a discussion about commercial culture in the United States. There were a number of seminars on Commercial Culture during the fall of 1986; while there is no date on the tape label, the age of the cassette itself indicates that this recording may be from part of a series at this time.
      Commercialism; urban development; Community development, Urban; Urbanization.; Blackmar, Elizabeth, 1950-
    - Carol Vance, Undated; cuid4198; 180632; 1 sound cassettes (Box 72, Folder 104)
      Content is so faint that it is nearly inaudible and cannot be discerned.
    - Russian Avant-Garde and Abstract Painters, Probably around 1979-81; cuid4199; 180633; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 56 minutes (Box 72, Folder 105)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:41
      George Costakis discusses the history of Russian art and artists from the late 19th and early 20th centuries. He touches on Russian avant-garde and abstract movements and includes artists such as Alexander Rodchenko and Wassily Kandinsky. He mentions feeling empathetic toward contemporary art movements in Poland because of the Soviet imposed government, indicating the recording was made sometime during the Cold War. Given the year of the tape's manufacture, it was likely the mid-late 1970s.
      Russia.; Art.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); Kandinsky, Wassily, 1866-1944; Costakis, Georgi; Rodchenko, Aleksandr Mikhaĭlovich, 1891-1956
    - Poverty and Economics Through the Religious Lens, Undated; cuid4200; 180634; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 34 minutes (Box 72, Folder 106)
      Economist Samuel Bowles examines poverty and economics through a religious and philosophical lens, referring specifically to Latin American poverty. He also touches on the work of Gustavo Gutiérrez.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:42
      Latin America.; Latin America -- Economic conditions.; Economics.; Economic development |z Latin America.; Economic assistance, American |z Latin America.; Bowles, Samuel; Gutiérrez, Gustavo, 1928
    - Brazil Classics Vol. 1: Beleza Tropical (Various Artists), October, 1989; cuid4201; 180635; 1 sound cassettes (Box 72, Folder 107)
      This is actually a commercially released compilation album entitled "Brazil Classics, Vol. 1: Beleza Tropical." Full of Latin and Tropicalia songs by artists such as Milton Nascimento and Nazare Pereira, this album was compiled by the Talk Heads front man David Byrne and released in October of 1989.
      Brazil.
    - On the South African Apartheid System, cuid4202; 180636; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 53 minutes (Box 72, Folder 108)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:43.
      Physical/Technical notes
      Recorded on both sides of a TDK Normal Bias 120 us EQ D90 Audiocassette, manufactured between 1982 and 1984.
      South African painter and writer discusses the system of South African Apartheid.
      Apartheid; South Africa; Breytenbach, Breyten
    - New Directorial Methods for King Lear, 2003 or 2004; cuid4203; 180637; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 64 minutes (Box 72, Folder 109)
      British theater director and actor Jonathan Miller discusses his upcoming production of King Lear at Lincoln Center in New York City. He speaks directly for about 15 minutes and then engages in Q&A with the audience.
      Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. King Lear.; Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts; Miller, Jonathan, 1934-; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616
    - Depiction of Fashion and Dress in Early Cinema, Undated; cuid4204; 180642; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 89 minutes (Box 72, Folder 110)
      This tape is labeled "Censorship Seminar 2/25, SCAMMEL," which may have been referencing a talk given by author and translator Michael Scammell during the February 25 session of the NYIH 1982 Censorship Seminar. However, on listening to the tape, the content is of a discussion and slideshow lead by art historian Anne Hollander. Hollander, an art historian whose focus is on the pictorial depiction of dress and fashion in works of art throughout history discusses fashion and clothing in early cinema.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 11:45 & 11:46
      Related Materials
      Other recordings from the Censorship Seminar are located in Box 39, folders 13 and 14.
      Fashion -- History; Film.; Fashion; Fashion in art; Silent films; Hollander, Anne
    - Live Scriptreading of an Unidentified Play, Undated; cuid4205; 180644; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 26 minutes (Box 72, Folder 111)
      Recording is a section of a play reading. Consists mostly of dialog between a younger man and and older man about their trust or distrust of women. The younger man appears to have feelings for the older man's wife. The younger man is leaving soon for Australia, a trip which will first take him by train and then by ship, indicating that it is a period piece or written during the days of ocean liners. A Google search for quotes from the script yielded no identifying results.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:38
    - Coma and After: The Experience of Consciousness, 06-Apr-01; cuid4206; 180647; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 66 minutes (Box 72, Folder 112)
      Psychologist Martin Kace discusses consciousness and emerging from a coma after a spinal accident that left him paralyzed. He was struck by a falling tree, breaking several vertabrate. He was in a coma for four weeks. He (and his doctor) discuss consciousness and coma from medical, psychological, neurological, and philosophical perspectives.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:47
      Consciousness; Spinal cord -- Wounds and injuries; Paralysis; Loss of consciousness; Kase, Martin
    - Light and Life in Los Angeles., After 1998; cuid4207; 247739; Waldie, D.J.; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 63 minutes (Box 72, Folder 115)
      Introduced by Ren Weschler, essayist Don (D.J.) Waldie discusses light, art, and life in Los Angeles. Waldie introduces his topic by referencing a February 1998 New Yorker article written by Weschler, in which he quotes Waldie about the remarkable quality of light in Los Angeles.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:23
    - Jung: A Biography, Probably 2004; cuid4208; 247740; Bair, Deirdre; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 62 minutes (Box 72, Folder 116)
      Deirdre Bair discusses her most recent (2004) biography, Jung: A Biography.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:24
      Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961
    - Visual Memory and Imagery, Undated; cuid4209; 247741; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 70 minutes (Box 72, Folder 117)
      Oliver Sacks discusses an inquiry he is working on at the time dealing with visual memory, visual imagery and visualization. He draws on his own experience as a person with Prosopagnosia or face blindness - a brain disorder characterized by the inability to recognize faces.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:25
      Memory; Prosopagnosia; Memory disorders; Sacks, Oliver W.
    - Tuscany: Inside the Light, Undated; cuid4210; 247742; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 70 minutes (Box 72, Folder 118)
      Husband and wife collaborators, Joel Meyerowitz and Maggie Barrett discuss their work on a photography book about Tuscany, Italy. Meyerowitz also makes references to his creating a photographic historic record of Ground Zero in the wake of the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks, which he was working on simultaneously. While they started this project in 2001, the book was not published until 2010, making it difficult to date the recording.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:26
      Tuscany (Italy); Italy; Photography; Barrett, Maggie; Meyerowitz, Joel, 1938-
    - River of Shadows: Eadweard Muybridge and the Technological Wild West., Probably 2004; cuid4211; 247744; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 59 minutes (Box 72, Folder 120)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:27
      Author Rebecca Solnit discusses the work of photographer Eadward Muybridge, paying particular attention to his photos of Native Americans and the Modoc War in the 1870s. She had recently written a book about Muybridge and his work in the American West, entitled River of Shadows: Eadweard Muybridge and the Technological Wild West.
      Modoc Indians -- Wars, 1873; Indians of North America.; Photography; Photography |z United States.; Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904; Solnit, Rebecca
    - Cultural Shock from Traumatic Events, About 2003; cuid4212; 247745; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 67 minutes (Box 72, Folder 121)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 11:28
      Former NYIH Fellow, Wolfgang Schivelbusch discusses the nature of shock taking into consideration both recent and distant events, specifically referencing the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001 as well as World War I. He goes into events as "raw events" and then what the media portrays and creates in its wake.
      World War |y 1914-1918 |x History; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Schivelbusch, Wolfgang
    - New York City Street Photography Slideshow Narration, undated; cuid4213; 247746; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 16 minutes (Box 72, Folder 122)